<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>field noise</title>
 <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-12-16T22:17:21-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://fieldnoise.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Craig Eley</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Hum and Sing - Ethan Rose</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2014/07/25/hum-and-sing/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2014/07/25/hum-and-sing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This morning while doing some packing I had a chance to catch up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://theradius.us/&quot;&gt;Radius&lt;/a&gt;, a fantastic podcast and radio show featuring live-recorded compositions, experimental music and sound art. They are currently in the middle of &lt;a href=&quot;http://theradius.us/grids&quot;&gt;GRIDS&lt;/a&gt;, a series of four commissioned broadcasts at Chicago-area electrical stations. Series episode 51 features a work by Ethan Rose called “Hum,” a droning interplay between the human voice and the electrical apparatus. You can listen to the entire 60-minute piece below, and read a &lt;a href=&quot;http://motherboard.vice.com/read/ethan-roses-hum-a-human-choir-sings-the-songs-of-americas-power-grid&quot;&gt;write-up over at Vice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/151452427&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first came across Rose’s work back in 2010, when he did a collaboration with songwriter Laura Gibson called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bridgecarols.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bridge Carols&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is absolutely stunning. Here is the video for “Younger”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/7289284&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sound Systems and Animal Death</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2014/05/23/horse-dies-at-churchill-sound-system-blamed/"/>
   <updated>2014-05-23T09:49:46-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2014/05/23/horse-dies-at-churchill-sound-system-blamed</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A heartbroken Wirth later said the horse was startled by what Wirth thinks was the sound of a starting gate bell coming from a commercial on Churchills massive new video board. The system includes 750 speakers. “We teach horses to break from that,” he said. “And you’ve got it on a loud speaker that everybody in a two-city block can hear. Well, what’s she going to do? She thinks shes supposed to take off. And thats what she did. And when she did, she lunged and she lost her balance and went down.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s from a &lt;a href=&quot;http://espn.go.com/horse-racing/story/_/id/10971859ever-tell-lynda-dies-freak-fall-churchill-downs&quot;&gt;devastating story&lt;/a&gt; from ESPN this morning on how a loud sound may have been responsible for the death of a horse. Theres a lot to consider hereincluding the ethics of horse racing itselfbut it reaffirms for me how much there is to be done at the intersection of sound studies and animal studies from both the sciences and the humanities.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Earth/Sound/Apps</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/22/help-scientists-record-one-day-of-sound-on-earth/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-22T14:42:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/22/help-scientists-record-one-day-of-sound-on-earth</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2014/04/soundscape-recorder/&quot;&gt;Help Scientists Record One Day of Sound on Earth&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bryan Pijanowski wants to capture the sounds of the world on a single  day, and he needs your help. Beginning on Earth Day of this year,  Pijanowski hopes to enlist thousands of people in recording a few  minutes of their everyday surroundings with his Soundscape Recorder  smartphone app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I have yet to meet Bryan, I’ve been lucky enough to recently meet some of the people working directly with him (some at &lt;a href=&quot;http://sites.psu.edu/soundscienceenvironment2014/&quot;&gt;the recent workshop that I co-organized&lt;/a&gt;). I actually used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/soundscape-recorder/id836741158?mt=8&quot;&gt;Soundscape Recorder&lt;/a&gt; app this morning with my students, and it was a really successful and interesting exercise. Luckily, most of my students have smart phones—though not all of them had the up-to-date operating systems required for the app—so we paired up and walked around Penn State’s campus capturing some local sounds, from the Creamery to the Arboretum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the recording process, the app asks you a bunch of questions, ranging from the factual (what did you hear?) to the loaded (how did it make you feel?). This gave the class a chance to discuss both what we recorded and the assumptions inherent in the act of recording and built-in to the app itself.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hearing Cornell's First Birds</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/21/hearing-cornells-first-birds/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-21T09:44:07-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/21/hearing-cornells-first-birds</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In honor of (early) Earth Day, here are some early recordings—in fact, they may be the first recordings officially done at the Cornell Lab of Ornithology. Tomorrow in class, I assigned some primary documents about the history of wildlife recording in the U.S., specifically the work of the Ornithology Lab in the 1920s. In digging up some almost-forgotten dissertation research and connecting some new dots, I’m pretty sure I can now can place the first recordings of wild birds that the ornithologists there recorded: a Rose-breasted Grosbeak and a Song Sparrow, both captured just outside of Ithaca on May 18, 1929.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(As an aside, it is almost impossible to prove that these kinds of “firsts” are actually “the first,” and in fact that isn’t super important to my work [or the narrative of the class], which tries to put these recordings into a much larger social and cultural context. But still, this kind of archival stuff is fun.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 1938 article for &lt;em&gt;The Journal of the Society of Motion Picture Engineers&lt;/em&gt;, Cornell Professor Peter Paul Kellogg discusses the outset of the recording projects at Cornell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In May 1929, the Fox-Case Company sent out two men with equipment to  Auburn, NY, to record sound pictures of wild birds for a springtime  release. After spending considerable time about Auburn, with no  success, they came to Cornell to enlist the help of Professor A.A.  Allen, to make the birds hold still. From his long experience with  bird photography Dr. Allen was able to help them out, and that morning  songs of three common birds were recorded synchronously with motion  pictures. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1474106&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1474106&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you search the archive of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://macaulaylibrary.org/&quot;&gt;Macaulay Library&lt;/a&gt; for recordings done in May 1929, you get two results: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://macaulaylibrary.org/audio/16968&quot;&gt;Rose-breasted Grosbeak&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://macaulaylibrary.org/audio/16737&quot;&gt;Song Sparrow&lt;/a&gt;. Whatever the third bird was that morning, it sadly did not make it into the online archive, and is probably lost to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you poke around a little bit on those pages, you can also find the links to directly download the files: &lt;a href=&quot;http://media2.macaulaylibrary.org/Audio/Audio1/1/16968.mp3&quot;&gt;Grosbeak&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://media2.macaulaylibrary.org/Audio/Audio1/1/16737.mp3&quot;&gt;Sparrow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy listening, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1474106&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;P.P. Kellogg, “Hunting the Songs of Vanishing Birds with a Microphone,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Society of Motion Picture Engineers&lt;/em&gt; 30.2 (February 1, 1938): 203. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1474106&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What's Left Behind</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/16/humanity-is-what-is-left-behind-when-all-media/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-16T16:33:56-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2014/04/16/humanity-is-what-is-left-behind-when-all-media</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Humanity is what is left behind when all media have been stripped out of our bodies and souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—John Durham Peters, “Helmholtz, Edison, and Sound History,” in &lt;em&gt;Memory Bytes: History, Technology, and Digital Culture&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Lauren Rabinovitz and Abraham Geil (Durham: Duke University Press, 2003), 198.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>fieldnoise 02 - water</title>
   <link href="http://fieldnoise.com/2013/08/29/the-second-chapter-in-my-effort-to-bring-the-field/"/>
   <updated>2013-08-29T15:45:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://fieldnoise.com/2013/08/29/the-second-chapter-in-my-effort-to-bring-the-field</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/107885221&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second chapter in my effort to bring the &lt;a href=&quot;/tagged/mixtapes&quot;&gt;field noise mix series&lt;/a&gt; back online is here, with this collection of water sounds, originally posted back in March 2011. In this 30 minutes you’ll hear the sounds of shrimp, whales, dolphins, and hippopotami; oceans, rivers, and streams; pianos, synthesizers, and singing—in fact, some of the most interesting and haunting singing I’ve ever heard. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fieldnoise mix 02: water&lt;/strong&gt;\ by craig eley\ (30:48)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;originally posted on March 9, 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. UN Greeting/Whale Greeting :: The Voyager Golden Record&lt;/strong&gt;:: (0:00-4:05):: The &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voyager_Golden_Record&quot;&gt;Voyager Golden Record&lt;/a&gt; stands as one of the coolest sound objects ever made: it was curated by Carl Sagan, plated in gold, and shot into space for eternity. In this clip, which was lifted from the 1992 CD-ROM reissue, various UN dignitaries offer their greetings (which alternate in stereo panning), and then, literally out of nowhere, there are whale sounds. Or ‘greetings,’ I suppose. The book that Sagan made about this record is called &lt;em&gt;Murmers of Earth&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s really worth checking out, though I don’t have it handy to see what he wrote about this track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;02. Vladimir Ussachevsky:: Underwater Waltz &lt;/strong&gt;::(4:05-5:23):: This is the first of three tracks on this mix that come from the venerable Folkways Science Series, which I’m obsessed with and will be the subject of a chapter in the dissertation. (These are actually all still for sale, so if you like ‘em, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.folkways.si.edu/searchresults.aspx?sPhrase=Science&amp;amp;sType=cat&quot;&gt;buy ‘em&lt;/a&gt;). This is a short little piano piece, from the 1957 album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.folkways.si.edu/albumdetails.aspx?itemid=1133&quot;&gt;Sounds of New Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;03. John C. Lilly :: Clicking and Whistling - Slow and Fast (edit)&lt;/strong&gt;:: (5:23-6:55):: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_C_Lilly&quot;&gt;John C. Lilly&lt;/a&gt; is the man who famously tried to teach dolphins how to speak English, and oversaw the experiment where Margaret Howe lived with a dolphin for 10 weeks and gave him hand jobs—&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldsstrangest.com/mental-floss/4-bizarre-experiments-that-should-never-be-repeated/&quot;&gt;I’m not making that up&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway, Lilly is a legend. He loved dolphins, and he drilled holes in their heads. He has an amazing &lt;a href=&quot;http://67.55.50.201/lilly/hub.html&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. This track is taken from his marvelous 1973 record, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.folkways.si.edu/albumdetails.aspx?itemid=1119&quot;&gt;Sounds and Ultra-Sounds of the Bottle-Nose Dolphin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;04. Jem Finer :: Water and Birds&lt;/strong&gt;:: (6:55-8:28):: This is a piece from Jem Finer—one of the dudes in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NrAwK9juhhY&quot;&gt;The Pogues&lt;/a&gt;—who has made a career change to experimental soundscape and sound art. He recently wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://longplayer.org/&quot;&gt;1000-year-long&lt;/a&gt; song. This track is from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gruenrekorder.de/?page_id=218&quot;&gt;Autumn Leaves&lt;/a&gt;: Field Recording and Soundscape compilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;05. Tony Papa :: Waterworks&lt;/strong&gt;:: (8:28-13:55):: From &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubu.com/sound/tellus_2.html&quot;&gt;Tellus #2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;06. Chris Watson :: Hippopotami Emerging from River Mara at Dusk&lt;/strong&gt;:: (13:26-19:05):: I basically wish I was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chriswatson.net/&quot;&gt;Chris Watson&lt;/a&gt;. Not only a legendary field recordist and all around interesting guy, but he also puts out his records on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.touchmusic.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Touch&lt;/a&gt;, alongside ambient/electronic luminaries like Fennesz and Philip Jeck. His album &lt;em&gt;Weather Report&lt;/em&gt; is widely &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/music/2007/nov/22/1000tohearbeforeyoudie3&quot;&gt;celebrated&lt;/a&gt;, but this is taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://touchshop.org/product_info.php?cPath=9&amp;amp;products_id=14&quot;&gt;Outside the Circle of Fire.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;07. Jenny Johnson :: Water Boy&lt;/strong&gt;::(15:23-16:02):: This is from an odd little record called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.folkways.si.edu/albumdetails.aspx?itemid=1111&quot;&gt;Vox Humana&lt;/a&gt;, which was designed to showcase vocal acrobatics. This excerpt is identified as “Water Boy” in the liner notes, but no composer or other information is given. If you know more about this song please let me know, I would love to hear other versions of it. This one is particularly noteworthy because Jenny Johnson, the singer, is singing “an octave below the usual contralto.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;08. Irving Teibel:: Psychologically Ultimate Seashore (edit)&lt;/strong&gt;::(21:17-24:27):: Fair warning: this mix ends with basically 10 minutes of New Age. I had to give respect to Irv Teibel, who passed away in October 2010 and is responsible for wildly popular &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environments_(series)&quot;&gt;Environments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; series of records in the 70s. According to Wikipedia, these were the first wave of mainstream environmental recordings for “relaxation” purposes, and some research I’ve done around this time confirms that. This is from the first in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09. David Behrman :: On the Other Ocean&lt;/strong&gt;:: (23:56-30:48):: Written in 1976 for flute, bassoon, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://de.academic.ru/pictures/dewiki/75/Kim-1-computer.jpg&quot;&gt;Kim-1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
